Hello. A lot of people love the anthem, the Marseillaise, the anthem of France.
But have you ever wondered what the backstory of the Marseillaise is?
Why it's so drenched in blood?
This is the episode where you will discover everything you ever want to know about the Marseillaise,
about ancient Rome, about the way the people dressed in the French Revolution,
and about the history of trousers. Don't miss it.
La Marseillaise, the song par excellence of the French Revolution,
or at least the one French Revolutionary song that everybody now remembers.
So, Tom, that was adopted as the official anthem of the French Republic in 1795,
but Napoleon didn't like it.
He didn't. He kind of pushed it back to the margins.
And then after the revolution, after Napoleon, Louis XVI's brothers,
Louis XVIII and Charles X, they come back.
They obviously hate it, so they ban it completely.
But the Marseillaise is never forgotten, and it ends up as the national anthem of France.
Would you, I mean, you are John Bull incarnate,
but would you agree that it's the greatest, the most thrilling national anthem ever written?
I mean, the most stirring?
Well, I saw you'd written this, and this is the sort of slack and lazy thing
that people who know only two national anthems say.
So they know their own, and they know one or two others.
If they're American, they say it's the American one.
If they're British, a particular kind of Britain, they say it's the French national anthem.
But actually, people who know a lot about national anthems,
know that the best national anthem by far,
so our assistant producer, Aaliyah, will back me up on this,
is the anthem of the German Democratic Republic,
Auf der Standen aus Rhenen, the anthem of East Germany,
which was an absolute banger,
and unquestionably the greatest national anthem ever written.
Well, Dominic, for those of us who aren't familiar with it,
would you like to sing it for us?
No.
No?
No, I wouldn't.
You're clearly afraid?
No, I just don't want to look like an absolute fool.
Ah, I don't think so.
Because obviously, as an Englishman,
my soul doesn't stir with patriotic fervor when I hear the Marseillaise,
except in Casablanca, that brilliant scene where
Yeah, they all stand up.
the Germans are sat around the piano.
Yeah.
And then Humphrey Bogart agrees that they can strike up the Marseillaise,
and it's sung with such fervor, and you are
Yeah, you love that.
Yeah, identifying with it, and it's very, very stirring.
However, I mean, it is worth mentioning,
for those who haven't looked closely,
at the lyrics, that they are incredibly martial.
Yeah, the bloody standard.
Yes, I mean, it's kind of blood everywhere.
Yeah.
And it is summoning the enfants de la patrie,
the children of the fatherland, to action.
In that first verse that Theo sung so beautifully,
France is menaced by ferocious soldiers
who are marching beneath this banner of tyranny,
which has been steeped in blood,
and they're coming to rip out the throats of,
patriotic Frenchmen's sons and wives.
And so this great summons to arms, citizens,
form your battalions, let's march, let's march,
and irrigate the soil with a tainted blood.
And the tainted blood is the blood of the tyrants and their armies.
Yeah, that tells you when it's written.
So war has been declared, but it also tells you about the mood at the time.
So we've talked a fair bit about the sort of paranoia, sense of conspiracy, sense of taint,
and impurity, and invading the virtuous body of the French Republic.
But tell us a little bit more, Tom.
I know you've done some digging into this.
Right.
How it comes to be written, and who by?
Well, it's written at a time when France is still a monarchy, just about.
So it's written on the 25th of April, 1792,
and that's five days after France has declared war on Austria.
And officers in Strasbourg, who are kind of pretty much on the front line,
there's a dinner, a public dinner,
and it's hosted by the mayor of Strasbourg,
who's a man called Philippe Dietrich.
And in one sense, he is the absolute embodiment of the intellectual revolution,
the Enlightenment-infused revolution.
So he's a Protestant.
He is a distinguished scientist.
He's a chemist.
He's a geologist.
He loves his Enlightenment ideals.
And he's a Freemason.
Yeah, total bore. Go on.
But what makes it intriguing is that he is simultaneously,
he is the epitome of everything that the revolution is opposed to,
because he is an iron master and an industrialist.
Now, I do like an iron master.
I know you do.
And his forges are being powered by all the timber and the wood that he's been harvesting,
and which the poor can no longer use to keep their pots boiling.
And so they're all starving.
So he's a figure of sinister wealth.
And he's actually a former aristocrat.
So he was the Baron de Dietrich.
So he embraces all the contradictions and ambivalences of the revolution.
And it's not surprising that he should be keen on reinvention,
the kind of reinvention that France itself in this period is having to undergo,
the process of going from a monarchy to a republic.
And it's, of course, they are on the frontier of a country at war.
And so at dinner, the toasts are offered exactly the kind that you can imagine.
So to the atri, to liberty, to the ruin of tyrants, to the fertilizing of the soil with their blood and the blood of tyrants, all of that.
And Dietrich, he finds all the words of these toasts stirring.
And he comments to the table, to the assembled officers, how tragic it is that all the marching songs that the French army have are rife with feudalism and superstition.
Yeah.
They derive from the Ancien Régime.
And he wishes that there was a marching song that would be appropriate to the new French army, an army of patriots and citizens.
And it so happens that at that dinner, there is a captain called Roger de Lisle.
And he is almost a kind of mini-Dietrich because he's a man of science.
He's an engineer. He's a freemason.
But he's also a part-time composer.
So he spent quite a lot of time in Paris rustling up
various forgettable songs that he's trying to kind of flog to theaters and so on.
But that night, the muse descends on him and he's inspired by Dietrich's suggestion.
He goes back to his quarters and he spends all night writing a song that he very catchily calls the Song of the Army of the Rhine.
And I think that if that, you know, if it had stayed, that had stayed its title, maybe it wouldn't be as successful as it proves to be.
And the next morning, he goes to the Dietrich.
And he gives it to Dietrich himself, who's very, very taken with it.
And Dietrich's musical.
And his wife sits down at the piano, plays the chords, and Dietrich bellows it out.
And they all say, this is amazing.
This is exactly what we need.
And so Madame Dietrich scores it for a military band.
And the band strikes up.
And it's kind of literally...
A revelation.
Because to quote David Andres in his wonderful book on the terror, he describes it as an almost millennial sense of drama.
And there is that sense, I think, in which it's a kind of secular dies irae.
Dies irae, you know, the great medieval account of souls being brought before the throne of God to be judged amid slaughter and chaos and bloodshed.
And the lamb, the sheep and the goats are separated out.
And this essentially...
Is what is happening in the drama of what will come to be called the Marseillaise.
Well, it has that apocalyptic sense, right?
That is so common in the political culture at this point.
So 1792.
I read with great relish that the Marseillaise music is probably not exactly plagiarized, but it's derivative.
So there are various antecedents.
There was an Italian composer called Viotti.
There was an oratoria by somebody called Grison.
And Mozart.
Mozart piano concerto.
Number 25, apparently, is disturbingly similar, Tom.
Well, remember that de Lisle has come to Strasbourg from Paris where he's been stationed and he's been hawking his stuff around all the concert halls and theatres.
He's got a knockoff tune that he's trying to pass off to Dietrich.
I guess in the way that minor composers, I gather, are often more prone to being influenced by things that they've heard than perhaps the very greatest composers.
And he's clearly not a very great composer.
But it wouldn't be surprising.
That he might perhaps unconsciously plagiarize certain tunes that he's heard.
Well, I mean, that's how musical composition works.
Yeah.
But the bottom line is that it starts to kind of go viral because soldiers from Strasbourg, whenever, you know, they various reasons they might be going back to into the heartlands of France and they take it with them.
They start kind of singing it.
And one of the soldiers who does this is going to Montpellier in the south of France and there on the 17th of June.
Um.
A doctor by the name of François Mireux hears it being sung by a soldier who's come from Strasbourg and he immediately recognizes it as something stirring, as something patriotic.
And he finds himself humming it and then singing it.
He gets the lyrics and five days later he is going to a meeting at the Jacobin headquarters in Marseille.
So he himself is a Jacobin.
He's a great enthusiast for the revolution.
And he goes to the.
Jacobin club in Marseille and he gives a very fiery speech and brilliantly he ends it by bursting into song and singing this, this, this tremendous song that he's heard from the soldier from Strasbourg and everyone at the club goes, yeah, this is fantastic.
And ask for the words to be written down and to be printed and to be distributed.
And quick question.
How does he know the song?
Like there are multiple, multiple verses.
How has he learned it?
He must have got it.
He must have got the lyrics from the soldier and the soldier must have got the lyrics.
Cause they've been printed off in Strasbourg.
Oh, they've been printed.
Okay.
Yeah.
So I assume that that's how it's been propagated.
And Miller is, I mean, he is, he is a hot Jacobin.
So we talked about how this great summons went out from the capital to enthusiasts for the revolution out in the provinces to come and celebrate the, the, the FET de la federation, which has begun to be celebrated annually on the, the anniversary of the storming of the revolution.
Of the Bastille on the 14th of July on the Chambre de Mars in Paris.
And so the people who come from the provinces to Paris to, to supplement the, uh, the, the, the guards that are available to the revolutionary authorities in Paris come to be called Federer.
Yeah.
And Mira has already enrolled himself as a Federer by this point.
And, um, he is part of a band of about 500 volunteers who've been recruited in the south and who are going to leave from Marseille.
And go to Paris to join the other Federer from across France and Mira is appointed to the general staff of this contingent of Federer who are going to march north and they duly leave on the 2nd of July.
They are armed to the teeth.
They are dragging artillery with them, heading off to Paris.
And as they march, they sing this song and the name that had been given to the song by, um, by, by Delille, the song of the army of the Ryan is obviously not suitable.
To a contingent of men coming from the south of France.
So they change it to the even more catchily named the war song of the armies on the borders.
And it's great.
And they marched up through from Marseille up towards Paris and everywhere they go, people absolutely love the song.
And by the time they come to Paris, I think that news of the song has preceded them.
And so they march into the city.
And the sound of their singing is electrifying for a city that is already.
Um,
On edge, excited, nervous in a kind of apocalyptic mood, fearing the worst, hoping for the best.
And it just strikes this incredible cord.
And it's a reminder of the fact that at this point with France poised between monarchy and a republic, there is a need for anthems, for new anthems that can channel identity in a way that previous anthems hadn't.
So if you think of, you know, the British national anthem, it's God save the king.
It's focused on the monarchy, but if you're going to get rid of a monarchy, you need new songs, new tunes, but you know, what's interesting about it though.
It's not entirely uncontested because in the next few months, there are lots of people who don't like the Marseillaise and who you actually use it as a stick to beat other people with.
So I read in Peter McPhee's great history of the French revolution that as the tension, the few between the Girondins and the Jacobin became more intense, the Girondins actually had a parody of the Marseillaise that they used as a kind of, they distributed that.
Or they did that later that year as a Christmas Carol by a guy called Antoine Joseph-Gorsas.
And it began, forward children of anarchy, the shameful day is upon us, the people blinded by their rage, raise the bloody knife.
So it actually turns all that stuff about blood on its head and makes it a song about anarchy and basically tarring the Jacobin as these sort of blood crazed fiends.
I mean, I think that an anxiety about the sanguinary quality of the lyrics has never been.
never entirely gone away. I mean, it's still, there are still occasional proposals in France
to this day that the lyrics perhaps should be rewritten to be slightly less carnivorous.
But conversely, it's the fact that it is so aggressive that means that people who are
caught up in the excitement of this new stage of the revolution, the second revolution,
as you called it in previous episodes, that's exactly what you want. You want something
that is no holds barred. And this song that comes to be called the Marseillais after these
people from Marseille, the Marseillais, clearly, I mean, it's absolutely what people on the
more radical fringes of the revolution want. And I think that it's not just the lyrics,
it's not just the tune. It's also the fact of who is singing it. So they're not professional
soldiers. They're not people who you would
expect under normal circumstances to be singing a marching song. These are citizens who are
answering the summons of their country in its hour of need. And of course they are also
implicitly Republican. They, you know, there is no mention of Kings of crowns of monarchy
in the lyrics whatsoever. And on the 14th of July, the date of the FED de la Federation,
this great celebration of the fall of the Bastille and the coming of the revolution,
they have a position of honor.
On the Champ de Mars. And the name that is given to this, this great open space is redolent
with a sense of antiquity because Champ de Mars in Latin is Campus Martius. And the Campus
Martius in ancient Rome is where citizens would assemble to go to war as citizens to
defend their country in its hour of need. And the fact that the Marseillais, the Marseillais,
are singing this song of kind of violent enthusiasm for civic values. It's giving to
what might seem terrifyingly novel, a kind of antique sheen because it's, it's giving
it a Roman quality. So Simon Sharma writing about the Marseillais, he, he, he, he says
of it that it's a great swelling anthem of patriotic communion. Nothing like the Marseillais
had ever been written that comes so near to expressing the comradeship of citizens. And,
and nothing ever will. But I think that for, for classically informed enthusiasts of the
revolution, actually there is a sense that perhaps when they're listening to it, they're
listening to the kind of song that might have inspired the Romans or the Spartans to go
to battle in shared citizenship.
So let's dig into this idea a little bit, because I think it's been such an interesting
theme running through the first series he did on the French revolution and this series
that we're doing at the moment.
Yeah.
Which is about the extent to which, well, the, the interesting kind of paradox that
on the one hand, the revolution is think that they're beginning the world again, and that's
what makes it different from the American war of independence or from the English civil
war or whatever, that there's a real sense that you can kind of reboot history and reboot
France. And yet at the same time, they're also conscious, very consciously role-playing
as ancient Romans, as Roman Republicans.
Yeah.
You know, the tennis court oath model on the earth of the Horatio, uh, I, I know you're
gonna talk about David's paintings.
So, so this is an idea that has run through 18th century culture, generally, hasn't it?
Enlightenment culture, a fascination with Rome.
I mean, Gibbon's decline and fall of the Roman empire, a great example of this, but it's
not all Rome, right?
So there are particular aspects of Roman culture in particular time periods that fascinate
them.
Right.
So it's not Christian Rome.
Um, and I think a huge part of the appeal of Rome is that.
Yeah.
That the, that the revolutionaries and indeed people in the enlightenment identify with
is the sense that this is offers a glimpse of a pre-Christian order.
Well, hence Gibbon, right?
So Gibbon is casting the Christian period as a dark age that, that, that modernity becomes
modern by going back to antiquity to the pre-Christian world.
So that's very important and particularly for the revolution as it becomes more and
more anti-clerical and, and indeed anti-Christian, but it's also, um, it's not the Rome of the
Caesars.
It's the Rome of the Republic and specifically the early Republic that is founded in the
wake of the expulsion of the Kings.
And the French revolutionaries kind of admiring that period of Roman history are obviously
following in the footsteps of the American revolutionaries who had cast their expulsion
of a King as something redolent of, you know, the spirit of Brutus and Horatius.
And it's telling, I think that even in the very earliest days of the revolution, long
before anyone is really considering getting rid of the monarchy, you do have radicals.
De Moulin would be a classic example.
He's doing this all the time who are comparing themselves to Brutus.
And there are two Brutuses in the history of the Republic.
There is the Brutus who leads the, um, overthrow of the monarchy and the establishment of the
Republic.
But there is also, of course, the Brutus who is descended from the first Brutus who murders
Julius Caesar.
And Julius Caesar is a product.
Product of the Republic who aspires to overthrow the Republic.
He's the Napoleon.
Well, absolutely.
So, so Napoleon, yes, but also all these shadowy figures that true revolutionaries are anxious
about hiding behind that, you know, the mask of patriotism.
So, you know, if you're playing Marat or Robespierre or whoever denouncing, um, frauds, counter
revolutionaries, you can do so as a Brutus.
As a patriot committed to the defense of your country against a tyrant.
What was the thing we talked about the other day, Cicero, it was Cicero who exposed the
Catalan conspiracy.
Is that right?
That's the big thing that Cicero, and they're obsessed with Cicero, aren't they?
Haven't they all studied Cicero's speeches and things at school?
And actually you mentioned Robespierre.
So I found this quote, there's a woman called Rosalie Julien, um, who's a Jacquemin sympathizer
and her diaries and letters are always cited by all historians of the revolution.
She wrote of Robespierre that he is quote, a man who was, who is devoted to the public
with the generosity of the greatest men of antiquity.
This Robespierre is a real Roman.
Yeah.
And I mean, they have higher praise.
And you, you, you've talked to Cicero, um, and, uh, Timothy Tackett in his great book
on the coming of the terror.
I mean, he quotes this amazing statistic that in speeches and newspapers during the revolution,
Cicero would be cited 10 times more frequently than the contemporary philosopher.
Jean-Jacques Rousseau.
So you think of all the books and articles and essays that have been written about the
influence of Rousseau on the revolution, but Cicero is being quoted 10 times more.
I mean, its influence is obviously in one sense, elite.
Well, yeah, I was about to ask that most people don't go to school for a long period of time
and they don't study classics.
So is this just to most people in France, is this just a mad babble that members of
the metropolitan elite exchange with one another?
No.
I, so I, I think it's kind of in the way that people might quote Darwin or Freud or Marx
today without having read any of them.
You have a vague sense.
Right.
We would, we would never do that, Tom.
It has been known that, that people might drop these names without having read
them.
Right.
I mean, it's that kind of thing.
Yeah.
But I think it's also that it becomes kind of the mood music.
It becomes actually the coloring, literally the coloring, because this sense of what it
is to be a Roman.
And this is fostered above all, I think by someone that you've already mentioned, the
great artist, Jacques-Louis David, who is a painter who's obsessed by Rome and his paintings
are austere and self-consciously impregnated with a sense of the nobility of the early
age of the Roman Republic.
And again and again, his canvases are illustrating men who are prepared to devote their lives
to their country.
Maybe even to sacrifice their own children in its cause, who put patriotism above all
else.
Yeah.
And David is painting these even before the revolution breaks out.
So when the revolution happens and people look at his paintings, it's as though David
has already been illustrating for the revolutionaries what they're doing before they had even begun
to do it.
And how much is that because somebody like David is influenced?
We've talked about the influence of the American experiment.
So how much is this?
Because in America, people are already using that Roman model.
Because really, if you've separated from Britain and you're going to be a Protestant republic
on the shores of the Atlantic, doing something that's never been done before, you've only
got one historical analogy to grope for, which is the kind of classical world.
So are they doing it?
They're doing it in America.
And then is David, are people in France, do you think, actively copying that?
Are they informed by that?
They clearly are.
There are people in France who are very, very influenced by what is happening in America.
Lafayette, your friend, would be an obvious example.
Yeah.
Big admirer of Lafayette.
Jefferson is ambassador in that period.
Franklin had been a constant presence in Paris in the years before the revolution.
And there are certainly overt revolutionaries who are influenced by the example of the Americans.
But so, too, are, you know, even people in, say, in the train of Marie Antoinette, so that
the Processe de Lamballe that we'll be coming to in our next episode, she was a great admirer
of Franklin.
And she saw no contradiction between serving Marie Antoinette and being very close to her
and admiring the founding fathers of America and the example of the American Republic.
I think in David's case, there are huge shenanigans in his youth about whether he's going to be
able to get a scholarship to go to Rome.
And the kind of feeling that he should have had it, but he's always being kind of frustrated
in the chance to go.
And so when he finally arrives there, it's the chance to roam the eternal city is all
the more precious to him.
I don't think that America stands between David and his imaginings of early Rome.
And I think that the look that you get in his paintings, which is kind of austere and
lacking.
Lacking in any sense of kind of flummery and self-consciously antiquarian.
I think this is his own and under the revolution, he brings this style to public display because
people recognize that he's brilliant at the visuals and you know, as with so much else
in a revolutionary situation, people need a new look.
They need expressions of the revolution's identity that aren't drawing on what is being
repudiated.
And, and, and.
And so he's the person who, for instance, is coordinating these great festivals that
are being held on the Champ de Mars on Bastille day.
And of course, David entirely recognizes the Roman connotations of this, the Roman echoes
of it.
He's also he's organizing the when Voltaire's remains are brought to the, the Ponte on it's
you know, and the Pantheon is a, you know, it's the great temple in Rome built by Hadrian.
Well, it's kind of originally built by gripper and then rebuilt by Hadrian, but it's, it's
a very kind of Roman looking building.
So again, it's a kind of classical ceremony and, and the Pantheon had originally been
intended to be a church, but it's so it's this, again, this idea of replacing Christianity
with something that is Roman and revolutionary simultaneously.
And Lynn Hunt, who's written a lot about this is brilliant on all this.
I mean, she says there is no government without rituals and without symbols.
You need rituals, you need symbols, and therefore you need people who are able to create and
invent it.
Sorry, you said replacing Christianity, but they're not overtly thinking about replacing
Christianity at this point, surely there is an anti-clerical tinge to it, but they're
not thinking, you know, we are going to wipe away every last taint of, well, I, I mean,
as we'll see when we do the next episode hostility towards those priests who have refused to
swear the oath of allegiance to the revolution.
Yeah.
Well, it's on the verge of becoming literally murderous.
Yes.
Um, and you've talked yesterday about how legislation is brought in, in the wake of
the, um, the massacre at the, the Tuileries forbidding even those priests who have sworn
the oath to wear clerical garb in public.
And so it's, it's part of the climate of ideas.
I think that hostility to the priesthood inevitably spills into hostility towards Christianity
itself.
And the association of Christianity with reaction and superstition.
Throne and alter, it will come to be called is, is a really is becoming a very, very powerful
motivating factor.
And as the monarchy starts to totter.
So also does the church it's was initially the church that had, um, sanctioned the anointing
of Kings that had enshrined the monarchy as a kind of God given gift from the almighty.
And so to contemplate destroying the monarchy is also to question the influence that the
church has had.
And Christianity has had.
On centuries and centuries of French history.
And so it becomes part of what is to be rejected.
I, and I think this is what is going on at, at, at, at this period.
And so by rejecting the regime, rejecting Christianity, ancient Rome is the obvious
place that you turn to.
Yeah.
So there are lots of people who still can't read, right?
So how does it, so David's paintings or reproductions of them, I guess, engravings and so on must
be very important in, in diffusing this kind of classical.
Yeah.
This, this classical aesthetic.
But I read in your notes that there are also kind of souvenirs and things that people can
buy.
Um, so broaches and stuff.
Yeah.
So, um, you can, uh, you can buy, uh, broaches, which are stamped with the head of Brutus
and you can get pins in the form of the fast Jays and the fast Jays are the, the rods that
the lictors who were the bodyguards of elected magistrates in the Roman Republic would carry
in front.
And before.
Yeah.
And then as he walked through the forum or whatever.
So people are literally dressing up as fascists.
Right.
So for us, fast Jays have this kind of sinister connotation because they give the name to
fascism, but you can see in the seats of government in, in Washington, DC, the fast Jays are there.
They're an inheritance from the American revolution and the establishment of a Roman type Republic
there in exactly the way that, that, that the fast days are being used in the streets
of revolutionary Paris.
And it's fast.
You know, maybe that is an example of.
Yeah.
Maybe it's kind of an American influence, but I, again, I suspect not.
I think it's.
Right.
Part of the same impulse that both American and French revolutionaries are reaching for
this classical heritage because it's just kind of part of the air of what educated revolutionaries
are breathing.
Now let's talk now about how people look.
Because obviously in some of these David paintings, he actually has people dressed in Roman style.
So they looks like they might be wearing togas or whatever, and obviously people aren't walking
the streets of Paris.
I mean, they'd look ludicrous even by French revolutionary standards, but they are wearing
Roman style hats, aren't they?
They are just before we come to the Roman style hats.
I think Davy does actually struggle bringing the visuals of ancient Rome to the, the, the
heroic moments of the revolution.
So you mentioned the his, this great painting that he's attempting to do of the the oath
and the tennis court.
The moment when the the third estate emancipated.
Emancipates itself from feudalism and superstition, but he never finishes it.
And I think he's kind of struggling to show the the third estate as, as Roman.
He can't quite decide how to do it.
Is that not also the problem that while he's painting it, people who were previously good
people have since been either canceled or executed.
Yeah.
So it's like photographs in the Russian revolution where people next to Stalin suddenly vanish.
So, so that is a problem.
But one, one aspect of classical dress, which you, you alluded to, which is a tremendous
success is it becomes the kind of the emblematic symbol of of the Republic is that the Bonnet
Rouge, the red hat, the red bonnet, the red cap.
And it derives from a soft cap called by the Romans, the Pilius, which was given to slaves
when they were set free.
Yeah.
And it was used by the Brutus who assassinated Caesar.
He stamped it on his coins after the Caesar's assassination to illustrate the fact that
Rome, which had been enslaved by Caesar had now been set free by the tyrannicides.
And it it's conflated with a cap that had been worn by people called the Fridians who
lived in what is now Turkey.
It's also known as the Frigian cap and it's adopted by the revolutionaries from pretty
much from the start.
I mean, certainly by 1790, they are saying this is, you know, this is the perfect symbol
of liberty.
So as early as August 1790, proposals are being made in revolutionary and patriotic
journals that say, you know, cocks on church steeples should be pulled down and replaced
with the Bonnet Rouge.
That would look absolutely ridiculous.
Ludicrous.
Yeah, it would.
Yeah, it would look ludicrous.
And in the Cordelia club, which is the most radical of all the Jacobin clubs.
Um.
The thing is that no one can address the assembled delicates without putting on a Bonnet Rouge.
And so in case you forget one on the table, there are lots of Bonnet Rouge.
So if you have to step up, you can pick one up and put it on your head.
I mean, I think that's absolutely ridiculous, but anyway.
Yes.
And so there are people who think it's ridiculous.
And one of them actually is Robespierre because in spring 1792, a motion is brought before
the Jacobin club that all Jacobin should wear the Bonnet Rouge all the time.
And Robespierre who, you know, who loves a wig.
Yeah.
He loves a powdered wig.
He doesn't want to go around with a Bonnet Rouge on his perfectly coffered wig.
And so he says, it's ridiculous.
You know, a cockade is, is fine.
We don't need to, to go the full revolutionary bonnet.
Would they have to wear them in bed?
I don't know.
I mean, it's kind of a can of worms, isn't it?
Can of worms.
But I suppose unlike the cockade, which is kind of like a, it's kind of like a rosette,
isn't it?
Yeah.
It's like a political rosette.
A cockade is kind of more obvious as a marker of political loyalty.
But the Bonnet Rouge, if you are wearing the Bonnet Rouge, you were really kind of saying,
this is what I am.
This is what I'm about.
And so in a way, the emblematic moment of the second revolution that you were talking
about yesterday is when the, the people break into the Tuileries and they corner Louis and
you know, they make him drink a toast to the Republic.
But before he does that, they make him wear the Bonnet Rouge, the red hat.
It's interesting.
It's interesting is now how hats have this kind of political meaning.
Because you, you would think that there aren't equivalents today, but of course there are
because it was very controversial because people would often use pictures of when they
wanted to be disobliging about Jeremy Corbyn, they would have pictures of him wearing a
kind of, you know, I don't know, a Maoist hat or whatever it is he used to wear or a
kind of Russian star hat and hats do, I mean, think about top hats or bowler hats, top hats
do actually have an oddly charged kind of political significance.
Right.
And this is the, the, the.
The greatest example of that.
Yeah.
And it's recognized by contemporary.
So a contemporary observer is quoted by Aileen Ribeiro in her book on, on fashion in the
French revolution.
So this is a contemporary writing in 1792, the sight of a woolen Bonnet Rouge fills
the sans culotte with joy and let no one mock him for it.
His enthusiasm is both praiseworthy and well-founded.
He has been told that in Greece and Rome, this woolen cap was the symbol of freedom.
And the rallying sign for all those who hated despotism with this in mind, his first desire
is to become the owner of a Bonnet Rouge.
And what is fascinating, I think about that passage is the reference to sans culotte,
because it suggests how a symbol that is drawn from classical antiquity, which presupposes
a certain degree of education, you know, to be classically educated is essentially to
be educated is being paired with a style of dress that is emblematic of the slums of those
who don't.
They don't have the kind of classical education that the elites are expected to have.
And of course we, we talked about the, the word sans culotte yesterday about how to be
sans culotte, the culotte of the knee breaches that have become associated with the rich
and particularly with the aristocrats, you know, this is, this is the look working class.
So rather than culotte, you wear loose baggy trousers, the pantalon, you wear wooden clogs
and you wear a short jacket, um, which in French is, is le camagnol.
And this I learn from, uh, from Eileen Ribeiro, um, derived from Camagnola near Turin, which
was home of Italians who had then settled in Marseille.
So in other words, it's a particularly Marseillaise look.
Like the, like the song.
And again, it suggests the way in which the Marseillaise are kind of perfect standard
bearers for this new revolutionary spirit that is emerging in 1792.
Oh.
Well, a rough, tough port city, um, where people, I guess, are seen as maybe as incarnating
a different kind of France, but also more pure, a more authentic France.
Yes.
Perhaps than the city.
So the sans culotte, we talked about them a little bit, um, last time.
They are the kind of urban working class radicals, aren't they, of, of Paris.
They're not the very poorest.
Yeah.
So they're not just the working class.
No.
They're artisans.
They're not just artisans, but they're also revolutionary artisans.
Yeah.
So they have a class-based identity, but they also have an ideological identity.
And I think that what is fascinating about this period is that just as you were getting
the working masses, the sans culotte affecting a classical look that derives from the education
of the elites.
So also are you starting to get elites who are dressing like the masses?
And this is such a suggestive kind of cross fertilization.
Yeah.
So the key aspect of this is effectively trousers.
Basically, if you want to slum it, if you're trying to pass yourself off as more proletarian
than you are.
Yeah.
I mean, you could change your name or something or drop the D or whatever, but the best thing
to do is put on a pair of trousers because that then you'll look like that's, that's
the street look.
Yeah.
So the, the, the Girondin ministry, so that's Brisson and his allies who were appointed
as Louis' ministers in March, 1792, you know, they, they didn't last long.
Louis sacks them in a disastrous move.
But while they're in office, they are known as the sans-culottes ministry.
Yeah.
So these very, very educated men are being given the name of the sans-culottes.
And the most amazing example of this kind of class-based cross-dressing is the former
Duke of Orleans, the cousin of Louis the 16th himself, the man who had sponsored the kind
of the early radicalism in the Palais Real in the center of Paris, one of the richest,
best bred men in the whole kingdom.
Royal to his, you know, right the way in his blood.
And he has taken on the name Philippe Egalité, you know, Philippe Equality.
He, I have to say, I'm just going to say it right now.
He's one of the worst men in history.
He's a terrible man.
He behaves very badly to his cousin, as we will see towards the end of this week.
Yeah.
But in the summer of 1792, so while the massacre at the Tuileries is kicking off, while the
monarchy is in the process of collapse.
Philippe Egalité.
Yeah.
The former, the si devant Duke of Orleans is spotted by Madame Tussaud, the, the wax
works set up the wax works in London in due course, and she has a hilarious description
of him.
She says, he was wearing a short jacket, pantaloons and a round hat with a handkerchief worn sailor
fashion loose around the neck with the ends long and hanging down the shirt collar seen
above.
The hair cut short without powder.
So no Rospierre powder for Philippe Egalité and shoes tied with strings.
So essentially it's kind of quite sixties.
It's becoming cool for the upper classes and the elites to, to dress in a, a demotic manner.
It's simultaneously plebeian, working class, revolutionary and Roman because that detail,
the haircut short without powder, Madame Tussaud's description, she, she specifies that this
is a particular style and it's called the Titus style.
Um, and the name derives from the role of Titus.
Titus in a play by Voltaire that he'd written several decades before, and this had been
restaged in May, 1791.
It's a great celebration of kind of Republican liberty and so on, and had been played by
France's greatest actor.
And the name of this play is Brutus.
So this style of hair is simultaneously.
It's what you wear in the slums, in the working class areas of Paris, but it's also what you
wear if you want to affect a Roman look.
And so this, I think is why.
The Marseillaise has the impact that it does because it comes at exactly this moment when
the Roman and the working class are fusing in the broad culture of revolutionary Paris
and they are arriving in their car manual, you know, these, these jackets that are kind
of emblematic of the working classes they're marching in when they come to Paris.
The first areas that they go through are those that are very self-consciously working class.
So.
So the, particularly the area around where the Bastille had stood, but they're singing
a song that proclaims civic and martial virtue in a way that Romans might have done.
And of course, as we've said, they're then assembling on the Champ de Mars, the campus
marshes.
And it's unsurprising, you know, you, you said how the Girondins in due course will
be intimidated by it and put off by it and parody it.
Even at the time, of course, there are plenty of people in Paris who are, who are terrified
by this.
This display say Royalists in particular.
So there's an officer in the Royal guards who, who sees them, the Marseille coming into
Paris, singing this song.
And he writes that they are 500 fanatics, three quarters of them drunk, followed by
the dregs of the people.
But of course, Dominic there writes a man who is on the wrong side of history, the wrong
side of history.
Tom, I wondered if the, the wrong side of history would make an appearance and so it
has.
So we'll be back next time.
Won't we?
With a, a, a genuinely blood curdling story.
So if you thought there hadn't been enough blood and gold in the French revolution so
far, you will drink your fill next time because Tom will be getting into the.
September massacres and fans of the, the process Driebenboul, who we mentioned briefly in this
episode, and who we introduced in our very first episode on Marie Antoinette, she will
be making a reappearance, not to entirely positive effect.
And it's, it's fantastic.
It's a terrible story and a bloody one.
And we will be back with that in our next episode.
We'll be back very soon.
So à bientôt.
Au revoir.